<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Hansard xml:lang="EN" id="8096412">
	<StartPageNumber>1</StartPageNumber>
	<DocumentTitle>
		<DocumentName>OFFICIAL REPORT (HANSARD)</DocumentName>
	</DocumentTitle>
	<ExtractedInformation>
		<ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebate">House of Commons Debates</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="Volume">VOLUME 147</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="Number">NUMBER 001</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="Session">2nd SESSION</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="Parliament">41st PARLIAMENT</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="Date">Wednesday, October 16, 2013</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="SpeakerName">Speaker: The Honourable Andrew Scheer</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="Institution">HOUSE OF COMMONS</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="Country">CANADA</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="TOCNote">(Table of Contents appears at back of this issue.)</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="HeaderTitle">COMMONS DEBATES</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="HeaderDate">October 16, 2013</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="MetaDocumentCategory">DEBATES</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitle">Edited Hansard * Table of Contents * Number 001 (Official Version)</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitleEn">Official Report * Table of Contents * Number 001 (Official Version)</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitleFr">Compte rendu officiel * Table des matières * Numéro 001 (Version officielle)</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="MetaVolumeNumber">147</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="MetaNumberNumber">001</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumDay">16</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumMonth">10</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumYear">2013</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="MetaCreationTime">2013/10/16 16:30:00</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="MetaInstitution">House of Commons</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebateFr">Débats de la Chambre des communes</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebateEn">House of Commons Debates</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="ParliamentNumber">41</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="SessionNumber">2</ExtractedItem>
		<ExtractedItem Name="InCameraNote"></ExtractedItem></ExtractedInformation>
	<HansardBody>
		<Intro>
			<ParaText id="3436025">The House met at 4:30 p.m.</ParaText>
			<Prayer>Prayers</Prayer>
		</Intro>
		<OrderOfBusiness id="8096627" Rubric="Other"><CatchLine>Opening of Session</CatchLine><SubjectOfBusiness><Timestamp Hr="16" Mn="35">(1635)</Timestamp><FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096415"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3436026">It being Wednesday, we will have the singing of the national anthem led by the hon. member for <Affiliation DbId="170148" Type="2">Newmarket—Aurora</Affiliation>.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436027">[<I>Members sang the national anthem</I>]</ParaText></Content></Intervention>
				</SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness></OrderOfBusiness><OrderOfBusiness id="8096417" Rubric="Other"><OrderOfBusinessTitle>OPENING OF THE SECOND SESSION OF THE 41ST PARLIAMENT</OrderOfBusinessTitle><CatchLine>Opening of Session</CatchLine><SubjectOfBusiness id="8096418"><SubjectOfBusinessContent><ParaText id="3436028">The Parliament, which had been prorogued on September 13, 2013, met this day at Ottawa for the dispatch of business.

</ParaText><ParaText id="3436029">The House met at 4:30 p.m., the Speaker in the chair.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436030">The Speaker read a communication from the Secretary to the Governor General announcing that Their Excellencies, the Governor General and Sharon Johnston,  would arrive at the Peace Tower at 4:30 p.m. on Wednesday, October 16, 2013,  and that when it was indicated that all was in readiness Their Excellencies would proceed to the chamber of the Senate to formally open the second session of the 41st Parliament of Canada.</ParaText></SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness>
			<SubjectOfBusiness id="8096443"><FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Vacancies</SubjectOfBusinessTitle><SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Provencher, Toronto Centre, Brandon—Souris</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096427"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3436031">It is my duty to inform the House that vacancies have occurred in the representation: namely, Mr. Vic Toews, member for the electoral district of Provencher, by resignation effective July 9, 2013; Mr. Bob Rae, member for the electoral district of Toronto Centre, by resignation effective July 31, 2013; and Mr. Mervin Tweed, member for the electoral district of Brandon—Souris, by resignation effective August 31, 2013.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436032">Pursuant to subsection 25(1)(b) of the Parliament of Canada Act, I have addressed my warrant to the Chief Electoral Officer for the issue of a writ for the election of a member to fill these vacancies.</ParaText></Content></Intervention>
				</SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness>
			<SubjectOfBusiness id="8096446"><SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Opening of Session</SubjectOfBusinessTitle><SubjectOfBusinessContent><ParaText id="3436033">A message was delivered by the Usher of the Black Rod as follows:

</ParaText><ParaText id="3436034"><Quote><QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">Mr. Speaker, it is the pleasure of His Excellency the Governor General that this honourable chamber attend him immediately in the chamber of the Senate.

</QuotePara></Quote></ParaText><ParaText id="3436035">Accordingly the Speaker with the House went up to the Senate chamber.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436036"><I>And being returned to the Commons chamber: </I></ParaText></SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness>
			<SubjectOfBusiness id="8096557"><Timestamp Hr="18" Mn="10">(1810)</Timestamp><FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Private Members' Business</SubjectOfBusinessTitle><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096471"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3436037">I would like to make a statement concerning private members' business.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436038">As hon. members know, our Standing Orders provide for the continuance of private members’ business from session to session within a Parliament.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436039">In practical terms, this means that notwithstanding prorogation, the list for the consideration of private members' business established at the beginning of the 41st Parliament shall continue for the duration of this Parliament. </ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436040">As such, pursuant to Standing Order 86.1, all items of private members' business originating in the House of Commons that were listed on the Order Paper at the conclusion of the previous session are automatically reinstated to the Order Paper and shall be deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436041">All items will keep the same number as in the first session of the 41st Parliament. More specifically, all bills and motions standing on the list of items outside the order of precedence shall continue to stand. Bills that had met the notice requirement and were printed in the Order Paper but had not yet been introduced will be republished on the Order Paper under the heading “Introduction of Private Members' Bills”. Bills that had not yet been published on the order paper need to be recertified by the Office of the Law Clerk and Parliamentary Counsel and be resubmitted for publication on the notice paper.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436042">Of course all items in the order of precedence remain on the order of precedence or, as the case may be, are referred to the appropriate committee or sent to the Senate.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436043">Specifically, at prorogation there were three private members' bills originating in the House of Commons adopted at second reading and referred to committee. </ParaText><ParaText id="3436044">Therefore, pursuant to Standing Order 86.1, Bill <Document DbId="6254235" Type="4">C-458, an act respecting a national charities week and to amend the Income Tax Act (charitable and other gifts)</Document> is deemed referred to the Standing Committee on Finance.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436045">Bill <Document DbId="6251824" Type="4">C-478, An Act to amend the Criminal Code (increasing parole ineligibility)</Document>, is deemed referred to the Standing Committee on Justice and Human Rights.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436046">Bill <Document DbId="6251827" Type="4">C-489, an act to amend the Criminal Code and the Corrections and Conditional Release Act (restrictions on offenders)</Document> is deemed referred to the Standing Committee on Justice and Human Rights.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436047">Accordingly, pursuant to Standing Order 97.1, committees will be required to report on each of these reinstated private members’ bills within 60 sitting days of this statement.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436048">In addition, prior to prorogation, nine private members' bills originating in the House of Commons had been read the third time and passed. Therefore, pursuant to Standing Order 86.1, the following bills are deemed adopted at all stages and passed by the House: Bill <Document DbId="6251803" Type="4">C-217, an act to amend the Criminal Code (mischief relating to war memorials)</Document>; Bill <Document DbId="6254374" Type="4">C-266, an act to establish Pope John Paul II day</Document>; Bill <Document DbId="6251806" Type="4">C-279, an act to amend the Canadian Human Rights Act and the Criminal Code (gender identity)</Document>; Bill <Document DbId="6251809" Type="4">C-290, an act to amend the Criminal Code (sports betting)</Document>; Bill <Document DbId="6251812" Type="4">C-314, an act respecting the awareness of screening among women with dense breast tissue</Document>; Bill <Document DbId="6251815" Type="4">C-350, an act to amend the Corrections and Conditional Release Act (accountability of offenders)</Document>; Bill <Document DbId="6251818" Type="4">C-377, an act to amend the Income Tax Act (requirements for labour organizations)</Document>; Bill <Document DbId="6251821" Type="4">C-394, an act to amend the Criminal Code and the National Defence Act (criminal organization recruitment)</Document>; and Bill <Document DbId="6254379" Type="4">C-444, an act to amend the Criminal Code (personating peace officer or public officer)</Document>.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436049">Accordingly, a message will be sent to the Senate to inform it that this House has adopted these nine bills.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436050">Consideration of private members’ business will start on Thursday, October 17, 2013.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436051">As members may be aware, among the items in the order of precedence or deemed referred to committee, there are four bills standing in the name of members recently appointed as parliamentary secretaries who, by virtue of their office, are not eligible to propose items during the consideration of private members' business. </ParaText><ParaText id="3436052">Bill <Document DbId="6251884" Type="4">C-511, an act to amend the Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act (period of residence)</Document> and Bill <Document DbId="6251896" Type="4">C-517, an act to amend the Criminal Code (trafficking in persons)</Document> were awaiting debate at second reading in the order of precedence at the time of prorogation.</ParaText>
							<Timestamp Hr="18" Mn="15">(1815)</Timestamp><FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436053">Bill <Document DbId="6254235" Type="4">C-458, An Act respecting a National Charities Week and to amend the Income Tax Act (charitable and other gifts)</Document>, and Bill <Document DbId="6251824" Type="4">C-478, An Act to amend the Criminal Code (increasing parole ineligibility)</Document>, were in committee at the time of prorogation and, as stated earlier, have been returned there.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436054">This is in keeping with the principle expressed at pages 550-551 and 1125 of the <I>House of Commons Procedure and Practice, </I> second edition, which provides that bills remain on the order of precedence since they are in the possession of the House and only the House can take further decision on them.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436055"> These items are therefore without eligible sponsors but remain in the possession of the House or its committees. If no action is taken, at the appropriate time these items will eventually be dropped from the Order Paper, pursuant to Standing Order 94(2)(c). </ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436056">Hon. members will find at their desks a detailed explanatory note about private members’ business. I trust that these measures will assist the House in understanding how private members' business will be conducted in this session. The table officers are available to answer any questions members may have.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436057">I thank all members for their attention.</ParaText></Content></Intervention>
				</SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness><SubjectOfBusiness id="8096520"><SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Order Paper</SubjectOfBusinessTitle><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096473"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3436058">I wish to inform the House that in accordance with the representation made by the government pursuant to Standing Order 55(1), I have caused to be published a special Order Paper giving notice of government bills and motions.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436059">I therefore lay the relevant document upon the table. </ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436060">The <Affiliation DbId="182412" Type="7">House leader of the official opposition</Affiliation> is rising on a point of order.</ParaText></Content></Intervention>
				</SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness>
			<SubjectOfBusiness id="8096475"><SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Points of Order</SubjectOfBusinessTitle><SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Motion No. 2</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier><CatchLine>Points of Order</CatchLine><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Cullen" id="8096476"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="182412" Type="7">Mr. Nathan Cullen (House Leader of the Official Opposition, NDP)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3436061">Mr. Speaker, I apologize for the interruption, yet I am compelled by circumstances to rise on a point of order related to the special Order Paper you just tabled in this place and specifically to government business Motion No. 2.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436062"> This highly unusual and complex motion puts 13 separate questions before the House, all of which are capable of standing on their own and all of which should be debated and voted upon separately. The omnibus motion is very lengthy, but I will mention just a few items to give a sense of the broad, sweeping nature of what is before us, and I will offer some argument of the rules that guide Parliament, along with the convictions that Conservatives themselves had when they sat in opposition.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436063">The first part of the motion would allow the government to reinstate any and every bill it passed in the previous session to the last stage completed before the <Affiliation DbId="78738" Type="1">Prime Minister</Affiliation> prorogued Parliament, essentially attempting to de-prorogue and return to the legislative agenda that his prorogation cancelled.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436064">A second aspect is that the government would then link the remaking of the special committee on indigenous women that had been studying the critical issue of missing and murdered aboriginal women in Canada.</ParaText>
							<ParaText id="3436065"> It would also attempt to give direction to the procedure and House affairs committee to begin its vital work on making the members' expenses disclosure regime more open, mandatory, and consistent.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436066">Last, it would direct the House to not sit on November 1 in order to accommodate the Conservative caucus and its upcoming policy convention.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436067">The sponsor of this motion, the government House leader, is fully aware that the official opposition supports the last three aspects of this motion. To flip a now infamous quote on its head, the government simply will not take yes for an answer. </ParaText><ParaText id="3436068">The government House leader is also fully aware that we are strongly opposed to the first clause that would allow for an across-the-board reinstatement of all government bills, a legislative carte blanche to attempt to undo the natural consequences of the Conservatives' own decision to shut down Parliament. We find it particularly offensive for the government to use a solemn, non-partisan study on missing and murdered aboriginal women as a playing card in its attempt to try to force the opposition to grant it the power to reinstate its old legislative agenda.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436069">In addition to being ethically worrisome, the manoeuvre also runs counter to the rules of this House. Perhaps the government members are not swayed yet by my arguments, so allow me to use some of their own in support of my case.</ParaText>
							<ParaText id="3436070">The <Affiliation DbId="78738" Type="1">Prime Minister</Affiliation> will remember what his House leader, Carol Skelton, argued in 2002, when the Liberals tried this exact same tactic. She said: </ParaText><ParaText id="3436071"><Quote><QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">If this motion is allowed to stand as is, members will be forced to vote for the reinstatement of [bills] to ensure prebudget consultations and to save the good work of the special committee. The motion is wrong procedurally and is wrong ethically.</QuotePara></Quote></ParaText>
							<Timestamp Hr="18" Mn="20">(1820)</Timestamp><FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436072">Given that O'Brien and Bosc's second edition of <I>House of Commons Procedure and Practice</I> had not yet been published, she quoted the following from page 478 of Marleau and Montpetit:</ParaText><ParaText id="3436073"><Quote><QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">When a complicated motion comes before the House (for example, a motion containing two or more parts each capable of standing on its own), the Speaker has the authority to modify it and thereby facilitate decision-making for the House. When any Member objects to a motion that contains two or more distinct propositions, he or she may request that the motion be divided and that each proposition be debated and voted on separately.</QuotePara></Quote></ParaText><ParaText id="3436074">In 2002, Ms. Skelton referred to a case from June 15, when the Speaker concluded as follows:</ParaText><ParaText id="3436075"><Quote><QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">I must come to the conclusion that the motion before the House contains two propositions and since strong objections have been made to the effect that these two propositions should not be considered together, it is my duty to divide them.</QuotePara></Quote></ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436076">In 2002 we even heard from the current member for <Affiliation DbId="170662" Type="2">Vegreville—Wainwright</Affiliation>, who said:</ParaText><ParaText id="3436077"><Quote><QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">I would suggest that this is an opportunity for the government to demonstrate that it is serious about trying to make the House democratic by dividing this motion so that members of the House can vote on each motion separately. The current motion does not allow that.</QuotePara></Quote></ParaText><ParaText id="3436078">The current members for <Affiliation DbId="170512" Type="2">Cariboo—Prince George</Affiliation> and <Affiliation DbId="170722" Type="2">Central Nova</Affiliation>, our new <Affiliation DbId="194629" Type="4">Minister of Justice</Affiliation>, also made submissions in opposition to this kind of motion. </ParaText><ParaText id="3436079">Eleven years later they seem to have learned nothing from the failures of the previous government. I would ask that you, Mr. Speaker, review the precedents on this, review the motion placed on the Order Paper that you have just tabled, and come back to the House, as quickly as you are able, to divide the motion for both debate and votes.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436080">It is therefore your duty, Mr. Speaker, to rule on this kind of tactic. This is completely contrary to our rules and precedents and to the spirit of respectful negotiations that allows this institution to function properly.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436081">As a sign of good faith to my friends across the way, perhaps I can help speed up the passage of clause (m) of government business Motion No. 2, the one I have referred to. This is the part of the motion that changes the schedule of the House to allow the Conservative caucus members to get to their party convention in Calgary. This is a courtesy that is often extended, as you know, Mr. Speaker, to all major parties in the House when their conventions conflict with the sitting schedule of the House.</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436082">Therefore, I seek the unanimous consent of the House for the following motion, which is taken word for word from the government motion on today's Order Paper:</ParaText><ParaText id="3436083">“On Thursday, October 31, 2013, the hours of sitting and order of business of the House shall be that of a Friday, provided that (i) the time for filing of any notice be no later than 6:00 p.m., (ii) when the House adjourns it shall stand adjourned until Monday, November 4, 2013, and (iii) any recorded division in respect of a debatable motion requested on, or deferred to, October 31, 2013, shall be deemed to be deferred or further deferred, as the case may be, to the ordinary hour of daily adjournment on November 4, 2013.”</ParaText>
							<FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3436084">The coupling of the government's attempts to ram together all of its previous legislative agenda to something as important as the study and the pursuit of justice for missing and murdered aboriginal women, we find offensive. The government has the opportunity to decouple these statements and allow for a free and fair vote that is in line with our rules and the ethics of this place. I put that motion before you now, Mr. Speaker.</ParaText></Content></Intervention>
					<Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096478"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3436085">Does the hon. opposition House leader have the unanimous consent of the House to propose the motion?</ParaText><ParaText id="3436086"><B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436087"><B>Some hon. members:</B> No.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436088"><B>The Speaker:</B> There is no consent.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436089">I see the hon. member for <Affiliation DbId="170184" Type="2">Timmins—James Bay</Affiliation> rising. If he will be patient, we will get through orders of the day and then I have received notice from him.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436090">Is the hon. government House leader now rising on a point of order?</ParaText></Content></Intervention>
					<Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Van Loan" id="8096479"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170693" Type="4">Hon. Peter Van Loan (Leader of the Government in the House of Commons, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3436091">Mr. Speaker, yes. With regard to the point of order raised by the opposition House leader, I find it highly unusual that he raised it at this time. I do not know why he offered to do so before we even started entertaining the throne speech, as he will have ample opportunity to speak to this later.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436092">However, in brief, I would say that the motion that has been put before the House, proposed on the Order Paper as government Motion No. 2, represents a balanced approach to restore the business of the House to exactly what it was back in June. That included the ability to return government bills to the House to be entertained, but also to restore the mandate of every committee, whether that was a mandate that was established by the opposition or proposed by the opposition or otherwise. In fact, everyone's business is preserved. </ParaText><ParaText id="3436093">It is a balanced and fair approach so that no one on any side of the House, including the independents, who has an interest is prejudiced by the fact that we have prorogued. That is the simple purpose of the motion. It is balanced, it is fair, and what is more, it is entirely consistent with the past practice of the House. I expect I will return to this more fully when we are closer to actually debating the motion rather than today.</ParaText></Content></Intervention>
					<Timestamp Hr="18" Mn="25">(1825)</Timestamp><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096480"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3436094">I look forward to those further interventions on the point.</ParaText></Content></Intervention>
				</SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness><SubjectOfBusiness id="8096526"><SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Oaths of Office</SubjectOfBusinessTitle><CatchLine>Opening of Session</CatchLine><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Harper" id="8096484"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="78738" Type="1">Right Hon. Stephen Harper (Prime Minister, CPC) </Affiliation>
						</PersonSpeaking><Content><ProceduralText TocType="TPC" id="1">Bill C-1. Introduction and first reading</ProceduralText><ParaText id="3436095"> moved for leave to introduce Bill <Document DbId="6255364" Type="3">C-1, an act respecting the administration of oaths of office</Document>, and sought the unanimous consent of the House to have the bill printed.</ParaText><ParaText id="3436096"><B>The Speaker:</B> Does the Right Hon. Prime Minister have the unanimous consent of the House to have the bill printed?</ParaText><ParaText id="3436097"><B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
							<ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="2"> (Motions deemed adopted, bill read the first time and printed) </ProceduralText></Content></Intervention>
				</SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness>
			<SubjectOfBusiness id="8096528"><SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Speech from the Throne</SubjectOfBusinessTitle><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096485"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3436098">I have the honour to inform the House that when this House did attend His Excellency this day in the Senate chamber, His Excellency was pleased to make a speech to both Houses of Parliament. To prevent mistakes, I have obtained a copy, which is as follows: </ParaText></Content></Intervention>
					<ParaText id="3437238"><I>Honourable Senators,

</I></ParaText><ParaText id="3437239"><I>Members of the House of Commons,
</I></ParaText><ParaText id="3437240"><I>Ladies and gentlemen,

</I></ParaText><ParaText id="3437241">Let us begin this day together by honouring in silent reflection those whose lives were tragically taken at Lac-Mégantic.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437242">

I come before you today as one proud Canadian among a vast nation of these, sincere in congratulation on this opening day of the Second Session of the Forty-first Parliament of Canada. I bear the happy wishes and deep affection of Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II, Queen of Canada, whose family has this year been blessed with the birth of Prince George.

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437243">Parliamentarians, you gather today with the high confidence and higher expectation of Canadians. Remember that our nation has embraced a unique set of indelible qualities that must guide your deliberations in this Parliament.

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437244">Consider this: we are inclusive. We are 35 million people gathered from every part of the world. We welcome the contribution of all those who inhabit this land—from the first of us to the latest among us. This year, we celebrate the 250th anniversary of the Royal Proclamation. This extraordinary document is part of the legal foundation of our country. It recognized the rights of Aboriginal people in Canada for the first time and established the basis of their relations with the Crown. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437245">Consider this: we are honourable. People of peace, we use our military power sparingly; but when we do so we do so with full conviction, gathering our forces as men and women who believe that the freedoms we enjoy cannot be taken from us. This clarity focuses our might in terrible times. And wherever and whenever we unleash that might, we raise our grateful voices and our prayers to honour those who have stood in harm’s way for us.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437246">Consider this: we are selfless. Our survival has been sustained by humility and acceptance of our mutual interdependence. Giving lies in our very nature, certain in our hearts that none but the gift passed from an open hand will multiply as those we help better themselves, those they love and, at length, the country they call home.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437247">Consider this: we are smart. We deplore self-satisfaction, yearning rather for self-improvement. We love learning and cherish our right to it. We are united, prosperous and free precisely because we ensure that Canadians have opportunities to learn, excel, advance, and thus to contribute.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437248">Consider this: we are caring. Our abiding concern for the common good of our neighbours—in each community—makes us responsive. We do not abandon our fellows to scrape by in times of distress or natural disaster. Inspired by our common bond, we come swiftly and resiliently to the aid of those in need.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437249">Today, as we contemplate our 150th anniversary, the eyes and ears and expectations of Canadians turn toward this Parliament, in trust that those who stand here in their place will relentlessly advance and uphold ideas that are inclusive, honourable, selfless, smart and caring at every turn without fail. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437250">Let us not disappoint. And with that spirit and direction, let us turn now to the present. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437251">Two and a half years ago, Canadians gave our Government a strong mandate: a mandate to protect jobs and our economy; a mandate to keep taxes low; a mandate to make our families and communities safe.

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437252">Despite ongoing uncertainty and instability from beyond our shores, our Government remains focused on these priorities. We made tough choices—the right choices for Canadian families. The results are clear: more Canadians have good jobs than ever before; families are paying lower taxes; our financial house is in order.  </ParaText><ParaText id="3437253">As the world looks to recovery, a rare opportunity now lies before us as Canadians: the opportunity to build on our ingenuity, our immense natural wealth, and our values and stability; the opportunity to secure the future, for our generation, and our children’s generation. It is the opportunity to lead the world in security and prosperity—not for the sake of doing so, but so that Canadian families who work hard, pay their taxes and play by the rules can get ahead.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437254">This is Canada’s moment; together we will seize it.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437255">And as we do, we draw inspiration from our founders, leaders of courage and audacity. Nearly 150 years ago, they looked beyond narrow self-interest. They faced down incredible challenges—geographic, military, and economic. They were undaunted. They dared to seize the moment that history offered. Pioneers, then few in number, reached across a vast continent. They forged an independent country where none would have otherwise existed. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437256">In the words of Thomas D’Arcy McGee:</ParaText><ParaText id="3437257">“I see in the not remote distance one great nationality bound, like the shield of Achilles, by the blue rim of ocean. I see it quartered into many communities, each disposing of its internal affairs, but all bound together by free institutions...” 

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437258">With hard work, sacrifice and common sense, those Canadian men and women built this country. In so doing, they founded a constitutional democracy, among the most enduring history has known. As we look to the 150th anniversary of our Confederation, we are reminded that ours is a rich inheritance: a legacy of freedom; the birthright of all humanity and the courage to uphold it; the rule of law, and the institutions to protect it; respect for human dignity and diversity.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437259">Guided by these values, we Canadians—Aboriginal, French, English, people from all corners of the globe—strive together for our families and a brighter future. We are on the cusp of a moment that is uniquely Canada’s. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437260">Just as our founders dared, so too must we. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437261">We must seize this moment to secure prosperity, for Canadians now, and the generations to follow.

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437262"><B>1. Creating Jobs and Opportunities for Canadians </B></ParaText><ParaText id="3437263">Balanced Budgets and Reducing the Cost of Government</ParaText><ParaText id="3437264">Creating jobs and securing economic growth is and will remain our Government’s top priority.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437265">When disaster struck the world economy, our Government’s decisive and pragmatic leadership navigated Canada through the worst global recession in a generation.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437266">Even before the recession hit, our Government was prepared. It maintained budget surpluses and paid down billions from the national debt. It lowered taxes for Canadians and job-creating businesses.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437267">During the downturn, our Government’s Economic Action Plan took the steps necessary to safeguard our economy. It protected Canadian jobs. It invested in infrastructure and productivity. And it controlled spending, while maintaining growing transfers that support health care, education and retirement. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437268">In spite of continuing risks from beyond our shores, our Government is leading the world by example. It secured the commitment of the world’s largest economies to put in place credible plans to achieve financial sustainability. And it set clear targets to bring our own deficit down. Canada now leads the G7—in job creation; in income growth; and in keeping debt levels low. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437269">Canada is now among only a few countries in the world with a triple-A credit rating. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437270">By taking decisive action Canada has stayed strong where others have faltered. But we cannot be complacent. The global economy still faces significant risks from factors that we do not control. We must stay the course. And sound management remains our Government’s guide.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437271">Canadian families know they cannot prosper by continually spending more than they earn. Our Government is no different.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437272">Last year’s deficit was less than forecast. Our Government will balance the budget by 2015.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437273">And it will go further. Our Government will enshrine in law its successful and prudent approach. Our Government will introduce balanced-budget legislation. It will require balanced budgets during normal economic times, and concrete timelines for returning to balance in the event of an economic crisis.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437274">Our Government has already set an ambitious debt-to-GDP target of 25 per cent by 2021. And it will reduce that ratio to pre-recession levels by 2017.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437275">Just as our Government manages debt, so too is it tackling spending. Every day, Canadian families make tough choices about how to spend their hard-earned money. Guided by this example, our Government will continue reducing the size and cost of Government to ensure that taxpayers get value for money.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437276">Our Government will freeze the overall federal operating budget, which will continue to restrain hiring. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437278">Our Government will make further targeted reductions to internal government spending.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437277">Our Government will reform the way the federal system manages spending.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437279">Our Government will review federal assets; when it is in the best interest of Canadians, they will be sold. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437280">Our Government recognizes the value of a lean, competent and committed public service. Public Service pay and benefit levels will be reasonable, responsible, and in the public interest. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437281">Our Government has already reformed federal government pension plans, to ensure that parliamentarians and public servants pay their fair share. It will reform disability and sick-day entitlements and work with employees to get them back to work as soon as possible.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437282">Our Government will amend the Public Service Labour Relations Act to ensure that the Public Service is affordable, modern and high-performing. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437283">Our Government will increase performance accountability in the Public Service to provide better service to Canadians, at a reduced cost, and to better recognize dedicated and effective employees.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437284">And we will make government more efficient and responsive to Canadians--by, for example, moving from 63 different email systems to one.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437285"><I>Jobs for Canadians </I></ParaText><ParaText id="3437286">Canadians want good, well-paying, stable jobs. And our country needs Canadians working. 

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437287">Canadians know that businesses create jobs. So our Government lowered their tax burden and cut red tape. 

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437288">Canada now has the best job creation record in the G7—one million net new jobs since the depths of the recession. These are overwhelmingly full-time, well-paying, private sector jobs. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437289">But our Government is not stopping here. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437290">Canada has one of the best-educated workforces in the world. But there are too many people without jobs and too many jobs without people.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437291">To address this job creation gap, our Government is implementing the Canada Job Grant. It will increase employment by ensuring Canadians are able to fill job vacancies. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437292">Our Government will take further steps to see that those traditionally under-represented in the workforce, including people with disabilities, youth, and Aboriginal Canadians, find the job-training they need. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437293">Our Government will work with provinces and territories on a new generation of labour market agreements to more effectively connect Canadians with disabilities to employers and in-demand jobs.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437294">Canada’s youth unemployment rate is already much lower than many advanced countries. But it remains too high. Our Government will redirect federal investments in youth employment to provide real-life work experience in high-demand fields.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437295">Our Government recognizes the tremendous potential of Canada’s First Nations, Métis and Inuit populations to strengthen the growing Canadian economy. It will continue working with First Nations to develop stronger, more effective, and more accountable on-reserve education systems. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437296">In a dynamic economy, workers must be able to use their skills, wherever in Canada they choose to work. Provincial borders should not be employment barriers. Our Government will work with provinces and territories to improve credential recognition and enable the free movement of skilled workers.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437297">Our Government will ensure that Canadians are aware of the opportunities offered by the skilled trades, and will assist apprentices with the cost of their training. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437298">Our Government will complete reforms to the Temporary Foreign Worker Program to ensure that Canadians always have the first chance at available jobs.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437299">And our Government will continue to create the conditions for new and better jobs for Canadians across all sectors of our economy.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437300"><I>Trade</I></ParaText><ParaText id="3437301">From the days of the coureurs des bois and the Hudson’s Bay Company, Canada has been a trading nation. Today, with one in five Canadian jobs dependent on exports, our prosperity hinges on opening new markets for Canadian goods, services and investment. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437302">This is why our Government launched the most ambitious trade agenda in Canadian history. In less than seven years, Canada has concluded new free-trade agreements with nine countries and our Government is negotiating further agreements involving more than 60 others. 

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437303">The Government will soon complete negotiations on a comprehensive economic and trade agreement with the European Union. This agreement has the potential to create 80,000 new Canadian jobs.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437304">Our Government is also committed to expanding trade with emerging markets in Asia and the Americas through our engagement in the Trans-Pacific Partnership and active negotiations with Japan, South Korea, and India. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437305">To further promote the success of Canadian exporters, our Government will launch a comprehensive new plan to assist Canadian businesses as they expand abroad. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437306">The United States remains Canada’s biggest and best customer. Our Government will continue implementing the Beyond the Border and Regulatory Cooperation Action Plans to speed the flow of people, goods and services between our two countries.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437307">Here at home, our Government will continue to work to remove barriers to trade between provinces and territories that cost jobs, inconvenience Canadians, and defy common sense. For instance, our Government will work with British Columbia and Ontario, and other willing jurisdictions, to set up a cooperative regulatory system for securities and capital markets.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437308">And our Government will amend the Importation of Intoxicating Liquors Act to allow Canadians to take beer and spirits across provincial boundaries for their own use.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437309"><I>Resource Development</I></ParaText><ParaText id="3437310">Since Canada’s earliest days, our economy has been built on our abundant natural resources. Directly and indirectly, the natural resource sector employs 1.8 million Canadians, many in skilled, high-paying jobs. Resource development generates 30 billion dollars annually in revenue that supports health care, education and programs Canadians cherish.  </ParaText><ParaText id="3437311">Canada’s energy reserves are vast—sufficient to fuel our growing economy and supply international customers for generations to come. However, for Canadians to benefit fully from our natural resources we must be able to sell them. A lack of key infrastructure threatens to strand these resources at a time when global demand for Canadian energy is soaring.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437312">We must seize this moment. The window for gaining access to new markets will not remain open indefinitely. Now more than ever, our future prosperity depends on responsible development of these resources. At the same time, our Government has taken action to ensure that Canada’s resources do not fall under foreign government control. 

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437313">Our Government will continue to ensure that our natural resource sectors remain open to foreign investment when it is market-oriented and in the long-term interests of Canadians.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437314">Canada’s natural wealth is our national inheritance and our Government will ensure that the jobs and opportunities it brings are available to all Canadians. In particular, Canada’s Aboriginal peoples must have every opportunity to benefit. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437315">Our Government believes, and Canadians expect, that resource development must respect the environment. Our Government’s plan for responsible resource development includes measures to protect against spills and other risks to the environment and local communities. Our Government will:</ParaText><ParaText id="3437316">Enshrine the polluter-pay system into law;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437317">Set higher safety standards for companies operating offshore as well as those operating pipelines, and increase the required liability insurance;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437318">Re-introduce the Safeguarding Canada’s Seas and Skies Act, to protect our oceans and coasts; and</ParaText><ParaText id="3437319">Act on advice from the Expert Panel on Tanker Safety, to create a world-class tanker safety system in Canada.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437320"><I>Farms, Fisheries, Forestry

</I></ParaText><ParaText id="3437321">Canada was built on the work of farmers, fishermen, and foresters. They work hard to feed our families and sustain rural communities.</ParaText><ParaText id="3438565">Our Government will continue to protect and promote Canada’s traditional industries. 

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437322">Our Government has given farmers marketing freedom and is helping them adapt and innovate. It will continue to develop new markets around the world for Canadian products, while supporting supply management. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437323">Our Government has supported fishermen by ensuring proper management of fish stocks and by opening new markets worldwide. It will continue to be open to solutions, supported by fishermen, that strengthen the economic competitiveness of this traditional pillar of our coastal economy. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437324">Forestry remains essential to Canada’s rural economy, supporting almost 200,000 jobs across the country. Our Government secured and extended the softwood lumber agreement with the United States. And our Government will continue to support innovation and pursue new export opportunities for Canadian companies.   </ParaText><ParaText id="3437325"><I>Infrastructure</I></ParaText><ParaText id="3437326">Infrastructure investment creates jobs, supports trade, drives productivity and contributes in a fundamental way to growth and long-term prosperity.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437327">For Canadians balancing the pressures of work and daily life, investment in our roads, bridges and transportation networks means less congestion, shorter commutes and more time with family. That’s why, in Economic Action Plan 2013, our Government launched the new Building Canada Plan, the largest long-term federal commitment to infrastructure in Canadian history.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437328">Over the next decade, our Government will invest 70 billion dollars in federal, provincial, territorial and community infrastructure. Projects such as building subways in the Greater Toronto Area, replacing Montréal’s Champlain Bridge, building a new Windsor-Detroit crossing and constructing Vancouver’s Evergreen Line will create jobs across our country. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437329"><I>Shipbuilding and Manufacturing</I></ParaText><ParaText id="3437330">Our Government will work in partnership with industry to ensure that all major military purchases create high-quality jobs for Canadian workers. Our Government’s National Shipbuilding Plan will create 15,000 well-paying, skilled jobs over 30 years for Canadians and produce much-needed new ships for the Royal Canadian Navy and the Canadian Coast Guard.   </ParaText><ParaText id="3437331">Canada’s automotive and aerospace industries are also key parts of our economy. That’s why our Government renewed the Automotive Innovation Fund and improved the Strategic Aerospace and Defence Initiative. Both have a proven track record of generating results for Canadians—jobs, prosperity and increased foreign investment.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437332">To foster Canadian productivity and global competitiveness, our Government provided 1.4 billion dollars in tax relief to manufacturing companies investing in modern machinery and equipment. And our new Advanced Manufacturing Fund will support new products and production methods. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437333"><I>Science and Technology

</I></ParaText><ParaText id="3437334">Our Government’s leadership in science and technology helps Canadian business remain competitive while creating high-paying jobs. Since 2006, our Government has invested more than 9 billion dollars to support science, technology and innovative companies operating at the outer limits of knowledge. 

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437335">Canada now leads G7 countries in post-secondary research investment. 

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437336">Transformation of the National Research Council, doubling the Industrial Research Assistance Program, and the new Venture Capital Action Plan are all helping to promote greater commercialization of research and development.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437337">Building on this strong foundation, our Government will release an updated Science, Technology and Innovation Strategy.  </ParaText><ParaText id="3437338">Our Government will continue making targeted investments in science and innovation chains from laboratory to market in order to position Canada as a leader in the knowledge economy.  </ParaText><ParaText id="3437339">And our Government will continue to promote Canada as a world-class destination for international students.  </ParaText><ParaText id="3437340"><I>Small Business and Tourism</I></ParaText><ParaText id="3437341">Canada’s spectacular beauty attracts visitors from across the globe to every region of our country. These visitors create jobs and sustain local economies. Our Government will continue to work with industry partners to promote Canada as a top destination for tourism. 
</ParaText><ParaText id="3437342">Our Government has reduced the red tape burden on small and medium-sized businesses. There are now fewer regulations and the cost of red tape has been reduced by nearly 20 million dollars annually.   </ParaText><ParaText id="3437343">Our Government will introduce legislation to enshrine the One-for-One Rule in law: for every new regulation added, one must be removed.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437344">The Canada Revenue Agency will cut additional red tape and help businesses navigate the tax system.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437345">And, following our Government’s return to balanced budgets, it will look at ways to provide further tax relief to job-creating small businesses. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437346"><B>2. Supporting and Protecting Canadian Families</B></ParaText><ParaText id="3437347">Keeping Taxes Low</ParaText><ParaText id="3437348">Canadians work hard for their money. And we know families are better placed to make spending decisions than governments. That is why our Government has lowered taxes, year after year—for families, for businesses, for each and every Canadian.  </ParaText><ParaText id="3437349">For example, our Government:</ParaText><ParaText id="3437350">Cut the GST, from seven to six to five per cent;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437351">Created Tax Free Savings Accounts, which now benefit more than eight million Canadians; </ParaText><ParaText id="3437352">Established a 5,000-dollar tax credit for first-time home buyers;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437353">Reduced the lowest personal income tax rate and increased the basic personal exemption; </ParaText><ParaText id="3437354">Introduced income splitting for seniors;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437355">Brought in arts and fitness tax credits for our children; and </ParaText><ParaText id="3437356">Froze Employment Insurance premiums for the next three years, meaning that employees and employers will save 660 million dollars next year alone. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437357">Overall, the federal tax burden is at its lowest level in half a century. As a result of our Government’s low-tax plan, the average Canadian family now pays 3,200 dollars less in taxes every year. Our Government has a proven record of cutting taxes for Canadian families. We have delivered on our promises. And, once the budget is balanced, our Government is committed to greater tax relief for Canadian families.  </ParaText><ParaText id="3437358">Defending Canadian Consumers</ParaText><ParaText id="3437359">Canadian families work hard to make ends meet, and every dollar counts. While companies will look out for their bottom line, our Government is looking out for everyday Canadians.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437360">When Canadians make decisions about how to spend their money, they must be assured of a voice, a choice, and fair treatment. For example, although Canadians are among the most digitally connected in the world, we also pay some of the highest wireless rates in the developed world. As families know—especially families with teenagers—the monthly bills add up.

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437361">Our Government has already taken action to achieve greater competition. Canadians know that competition is good for everyone. Competition lowers prices and keeps businesses from becoming complacent. As a result, wireless rates have fallen nearly 20 per cent since 2008.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437362">But there is much more work to do. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437363">Our Government will take steps to reduce roaming costs on networks within Canada.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437364">Our Government believes Canadian families should be able to choose the combination of television channels they want. It will require channels to be unbundled, while protecting Canadian jobs.  </ParaText><ParaText id="3437365">Our Government will continue enhancing high-speed broadband networks for rural Canadians.  </ParaText><ParaText id="3437366">And our Government will take additional action to protect Canadian consumers. Canadians are tired of hidden fees. They deserve to know the real cost of paying by debit or credit card. And they should not be charged more in Canada for identical goods that sell for less in the United States.

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437367">Our Government will:

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437368">End “pay to pay” policies, so customers won’t pay extra to receive paper bills;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437369">Expand no-cost basic banking services;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437370"> 
Work with the provinces and territories to crack down on predatory payday lenders;
</ParaText><ParaText id="3437371">Empower consumers by requiring disclosure of the cost of different payment methods; and</ParaText><ParaText id="3437372">Take further action to end geographic price discrimination against Canadians.
</ParaText><ParaText id="3437373">Supporting Victims and Punishing Criminals</ParaText><ParaText id="3437374">Our Government believes that the justice system exists to protect law-abiding citizens and our communities. For too long, the voices of victims have been silenced, while the system coddled criminals. Our Government has worked to re-establish Canada as a country where those who break the law are punished for their actions; where penalties match the severity of crimes committed; where the rights of victims come before the rights of criminals.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437375">Our Government will introduce a Victims Bill of Rights to restore victims to their rightful place at the heart of our justice system. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437376">Our Government will focus on protecting the most vulnerable of all victims, our children. Recent tragic deaths, including those of Amanda Todd, Rehtaeh Parsons, and Todd Loik, have shocked Canadians. Our Government will introduce legislation giving police and prosecutors new tools to effectively address cyberbullying that involves criminal invasion of privacy, intimidation and personal abuse. This legislation would create a new criminal offence prohibiting the non-consensual distribution of intimate images. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437377">Canadians are rightfully alarmed when violent offenders found not criminally responsible for their actions are released into our communities. Our Government will re-introduce legislation to ensure that public safety comes first. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437378">But we must do even more to protect our children. Child predators should never be let off with only a single sentence for multiple crimes against children. Canadians demand that those who prey on our children pay the full price for every devastated life. Our Government will end sentencing discounts for child sex offenders. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437379">It is also unacceptable that dangerous and violent offenders are released into our communities before serving their full sentences. Our Government will end the practice of automatic early release for serious repeat offenders. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437380">But for the worst of all criminals, even this is not enough. Canadians do not understand why the most dangerous criminals would ever be released from prison. For them, our Government will change the law so that a life sentence means a sentence for life.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437381">Aboriginal women are disproportionately the victims of violent crime. Our Government will renew its efforts to address the issue of missing and murdered Aboriginal women. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437382">Canadians also know that prostitution victimizes women and threatens the safety of our communities. Our Government will vigorously defend the constitutionality of Canada’s prostitution laws.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437383">Finally, our Government recognizes the daily risks taken by police officers and their service animals. It will bring forward Quanto’s law in honour of them. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437384">Safeguarding Families and Communities</ParaText><ParaText id="3437385">Families are the cornerstone of our society. Families raise our children and build our communities. As our families succeed, Canada succeeds.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437386">Our Government understands the daily pressures ordinary Canadian families face. And it is working to strengthen families, not replace them. That’s why our Government took money from bureaucrats and lobbyists and gave it to the real experts on child care—mom and dad. Our Government’s Universal Child Care Benefit provides 1,200 dollars a year to parents to help with the costs of raising kids.

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437387">Our Government will also support hard-working Canadian families in other ways.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437388">Every day, parents make choices about what goes on the dinner table. Our Safe Food for Canadians Act was a significant milestone in strengthening Canada’s world-class food safety system. Our Government will work with the provinces and territories to further strengthen food inspection regimes. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437389">Our Government will consult with Canadian parents to improve the way nutritional information is presented on food labels. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437390">Our Government is also committed to ensuring that drug labels are written in plain language, and that the potential side effects of medication are accurately indicated. To help identify potentially dangerous drugs, and ensure the quick recall of unsafe drugs, it will introduce new patient safety legislation. This will include new powers to require reporting of adverse drug reactions.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437391">Our Government will also:</ParaText><ParaText id="3437392">Build on our caregiver tax credit by working with employers to better accommodate Canadians caring for older family members;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437393">Help seniors quickly access information about programs and services they need and use in their communities;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437394">Make adoption more affordable for Canadian families;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437395">Renew investments in health research to tackle the growing onset of dementia, and related illnesses;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437396">Prevent employers and insurance companies from discriminating against Canadians on the basis of genetic testing;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437397">Collaborate with injury prevention organizations, to reduce the injury rate in Canada; and</ParaText><ParaText id="3437398">Work with the provinces and territories and with the private and not-for-profit sectors to encourage young Canadians to be more physically active.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437399">Canadian families expect safe and healthy communities in which to raise their children. They want to address poverty and other persistent social problems, access safe and reliable infrastructure, and enjoy a clean and healthy environment.

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437400">Our Government will:</ParaText><ParaText id="3437401">Re-introduce and pass the Respect for Communities Act to ensure that parents have a say before drug injection sites open in their communities;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437402">Expand its National Anti-Drug Strategy to address the growing problem of prescription drug abuse;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437403">Close loopholes that allow for the feeding of addiction under the guise of treatment;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437404">Act on the opportunities presented by social finance and the successful National Call for Concepts for Social Finance;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437405">Build on the successful Housing First approach and its renewed Homelessness Partnering Strategy to help house vulnerable Canadians;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437406">Protect Canada’s rich natural heritage by unveiling a new National Conservation Plan to further increase protected areas, focusing on stronger marine and coastal conservation;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437407">Complete, by 2015, its work to protect wilderness lands in Nááts’ihch’oh, Bathurst Island and the Mealy Mountains;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437408">Work with communities, non-profit organizations, and businesses to create and protect more green space in our urban and suburban areas;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437409">Take further action to improve air quality nationwide; and</ParaText><ParaText id="3437410">Build on its record as the first government to achieve an absolute reduction in greenhouse gas emissions by working with provinces to reduce emissions from the oil and gas sectors while ensuring Canadian companies remain competitive. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437411">Since before Confederation, Canada has relied on railways for the movement of goods and passengers. It is no different today. New economic opportunities still require rail to link Canadian goods to waiting markets.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437412">Our Government has already amended the Railway Safety Act to further enhance the safety of rail transportation.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437413">As efforts to clean up and rebuild Lac-Mégantic demonstrate, railway companies must be able to bear the cost of their actions. Our Government will require shippers and railways to carry additional insurance so they are held accountable.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437414">And we will take targeted action to increase the safety of the transportation of dangerous goods.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437415">The first responders and ordinary Canadians who came together to confront the recent disasters in Lac-Mégantic and Alberta showed courage under the most dire circumstances. The Government has always stood with communities in times of crisis and recovery.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437416">Our Government will continue to support the citizens of Lac-Mégantic and affected communities in Alberta as they move forward.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437417">Building community resilience can mitigate the worst impacts of natural disasters and other emergencies before they happen. Our Government will work with provinces and territories to develop a National Disaster Mitigation Program, focused on reducing the impact of natural disasters.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437418"><B>3. Putting Canada First</B></ParaText><ParaText id="3437419">Supporting Our Armed Forces</ParaText><ParaText id="3437420">Government has no higher obligation than the protection of national sovereignty and the security of citizens. And Canadians know that you cannot earn respect by projecting weakness. Serious countries have serious capabilities. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437421">Look at the paintings that adorn this room—scenes of the Great War. They remind us of this, and of the profound sacrifices made by our men and women in uniform. These heroes are the pride of our country and the backbone of our history. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437422">After a decade of darkness, our Government has been living up to our promise to give the Canadian military the tools it needs to get the job done. Soldier for soldier, sailor for sailor, airman for airman, the Canadian Armed Forces are once again the best in the world.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437423">No longer does Canada have to hitch a ride with our allies. Our serving men and women can now carry out their vital missions. The Royal Canadian Air Force is flying new heavy-lift C-17 and C-130J transport aircraft, and operating Chinook helicopters. New tanks, artillery and other equipment have proven their worth in combat. Canadian workers at Canadian shipyards will build new ships for the Royal Canadian Navy and the Canadian Coast Guard. And our Government will complete our plan to replace Canada’s fleet of fighter jets.
</ParaText><ParaText id="3437424">Building on these successes, our Government will renew our Canada First Defence Strategy. Now and in the future, Canada’s Armed Forces will defend Canada and protect our borders; maintain sovereignty over our Northern lands and waters; fight alongside our allies to defend our interests; and respond to emergencies within Canada and around the world.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437425">To be effective, our military must have more teeth and less tail. Our Government will:</ParaText><ParaText id="3437426">Put front-line capability before back-office bureaucracy; </ParaText><ParaText id="3437427">Respond to emerging threats to our sovereignty and economy posed by terrorism and cyber-attacks, while ensuring Canadians’ fundamental privacy rights are protected; </ParaText><ParaText id="3437428">Incorporate a strong role for our military reserves, who are an essential link between the Armed Forces and Canadian communities; and </ParaText><ParaText id="3437429">Assist employers of reservists who are required to deploy on missions vital to the security of all Canadians.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437430">As our Government takes these steps, it will always keep faith with those who have defended Canada with pride. Our veterans have stood up for us; we will stand by them. Our Government has made unprecedented investments to support our veterans.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437431">Our Government has:</ParaText><ParaText id="3437432">Increased support through its enhanced Veterans Charter;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437433">Ensured dignified funerals for our injured veterans;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437434">Reduced red tape so veterans can access the benefits they need; and</ParaText><ParaText id="3437435">Invested almost five billion additional dollars in benefits and programs.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437436">Our Government has worked to help returning veterans re-establish themselves. We will:

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437437">Reach out to homeless veterans and help give them the support they need; and</ParaText><ParaText id="3437438">Build on our successful “Helmets to Hardhats” program to place veterans in good jobs. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437439">Canada’s Northern Sovereignty</ParaText><ParaText id="3437440">We are a northern country. We are a northern people. Canada’s greatest dreams are to be found in our highest latitudes. They are the dreams of a North confident and prosperous, the True North, strong and free.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437441">Our Government is securing our Northern sovereignty; promoting prosperity for Northerners; protecting our Arctic environmental heritage; and giving the people of the North a greater say in their own affairs. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437442">Our Government has made great strides by:</ParaText><ParaText id="3437443">Opening the Canadian Armed Forces Arctic Training Centre;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437444">Expanding the Canadian Rangers, our eyes and ears in the North; </ParaText><ParaText id="3437445">Creating the Canadian Northern Economic Development Agency;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437446">Mapping Canada’s Arctic seabed to assert our sovereignty; </ParaText><ParaText id="3437447">Investing in health care, education, and affordable housing for Northerners; and</ParaText><ParaText id="3437448">Concluding a historic Devolution Agreement with the Northwest Territories and negotiating one with Nunavut. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437449">But the eyes of the world increasingly look enviously to our North. Our Government will not rest. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437450">Our Government will fulfill Prime Minister Diefenbaker’s historic vision by completing the Dempster Highway to the Arctic Ocean, linking Canada from sea to sea to sea. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437451">Our Government has established the Canadian High Arctic Research Station. This world-class science and technology research facility will open in time for the 150th anniversary of Confederation.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437452">With the arrival of our Government’s new Arctic Offshore Patrol Ships, Canada’s first deep water Arctic port at Nanisivik will be operational. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437453">Our Government recognizes that the future prosperity of the North requires responsible development of its abundant natural resources. Northerners must benefit from this treasure. Our Government will work alongside Inuit, First Nations, territorial governments and industry to ensure that Northerners are well trained to take their full place in this new economy. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437454">Our Government will also continue to defend the seal hunt, an important source of food and income for coastal and Inuit communities. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437455">The story of the North is the story of Canada. In order to tell that story for Canada’s 150th year, our Government will continue efforts to solve one of the most enduring mysteries of our past. We will work with renewed determination and an expanded team of partners to discover the fate of Sir John Franklin’s lost Arctic expedition.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437456">Promoting Canadian Values</ParaText><ParaText id="3437457">Canada stands for what is right and good in the world. This is the true character of Canadians—honourable in our dealings, faithful to our commitments, loyal to our friends. Confident partners, courageous warriors and compassionate neighbours. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437458">Canada does not go along to get along. Our Government defends Israel’s right to exist as a Jewish state, the lone outpost of freedom and democracy in a dangerous region. And our Government stands opposed to those regimes that threaten their neighbours, slaughter their citizens, and imperil freedom. These regimes must ultimately be judged not by their words, but by their actions. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437459">Canada seeks a world where freedom—including freedom of religion, the rule of law, democracy and human dignity are respected. Our Government will continue to promote these fundamental values around the world, including through the newly established Office of Religious Freedom.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437460">And Canadians know that freedom and prosperity march together. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437461">Our Government will help the world’s neediest by partnering with the private sector to create economic growth in the developing world. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437462">Tax dollars spent on foreign aid must achieve real results. Our Government’s international aid will continue to be focused, effective and accountable. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437463">Canadians also know that free and healthy societies require the full participation of women. Canada has taken a leadership role in addressing the health challenges facing women, infants and children in the world’s poorest countries. These efforts are saving millions of lives. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437464">In particular, Canada recognizes the courageous and inspiring example set by Malala Yousafzai in risking her life promoting education for young women. She faced down evil and oppression and now speaks boldly for those who are silenced. Recognizing her heroism, our Government will, on behalf of all Canadians, bestow honorary citizenship on this remarkable young woman. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437465">Sadly, millions of women and girls continue to be brutalized by violence, including through the inhumane practice of early and forced marriage. This barbarism is unacceptable to Canadians. Our Government will take steps to ensure that it does not occur on our soil. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437466">It is the reality of our country that Canadians of very different origins live and work side by side, together. New Canadians work hard to learn our languages, our values, and our traditions, and in turn, are welcomed as equal members of the Canadian family. Our Government inherited a broken immigration system, and has worked hard to fix it.

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437467">Our Government has:</ParaText><ParaText id="3437468">Cut the backlog of applications by almost half;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437469">Eliminated the backlog for economic immigrants; </ParaText><ParaText id="3437470">Cut the right-of-landing fee in half;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437471">Lowered wait times for skilled workers coming to Canada; </ParaText><ParaText id="3437472">Increased protection for genuine refugees;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437473">Reduced the number of fraudulent asylum claimants and deported more than 100,000 illegal immigrants; and</ParaText><ParaText id="3437474">Remained on track to meet our goal of reuniting families faster. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437475">But there is still more our Government can and will do.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437476">We know that a job is the best path to social integration. Our Government will introduce a new model to select immigrants based on the skills Canadian employers need.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437477">Our Government will reform the Immigrant Investor Program so that these investors make a real contribution in exchange for the security and pathway to citizenship that Canada provides. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437478">Canadians understand that citizenship should not be simply a passport of convenience. Citizenship is a pledge of mutual responsibility and a shared commitment to values rooted in our history. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437479">Our Government will not hesitate to uphold the fundamental rights of all Canadians wherever they are threatened. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437480">To strengthen and protect the value of Canadian citizenship, our Government will introduce the first comprehensive reforms to the Citizenship Act in more than a generation.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437481">2017: Anniversary of Confederation</ParaText><ParaText id="3437482">As we look confidently to the future, we draw great strength from our past. Beginning with our Aboriginal peoples, Canada’s story is one of risk, sacrifice, and rugged determination. From the founding of New France, to the fight for Canada in the War of 1812; from the visionary achievement of Confederation, to our victory at Vimy Ridge, Canadians have repeatedly triumphed over long odds to forge a great country, united and free.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437483">It is a story we recall with wonder and recount with pride. A story of how different provinces founded a federation in which our distinct strengths advance our unity. A federation in which Canada's two national languages position us uniquely in the world; where francophones thrive and celebrate a unique culture, in solidarity with fellow Canadians. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437484">Our Government has recognized the Québécois as a nation within a united Canada. It will work with the Government of Québec to ensure our common prosperity. And our Government will continue to respect the division of jurisdiction at the heart of the Constitution adopted at Confederation.

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437485">Canada’s Confederation is worth celebrating. As we approach our historic 150th anniversary in 2017, our Government will join with Canadians in honouring this momentous milestone by: </ParaText><ParaText id="3437486">Marking the 150th anniversaries of the Charlottetown and Québec Conferences;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437487">Celebrating the 200th birthdays of two of our greatest Fathers of Confederation, Sir George-Étienne Cartier and Sir John A. Macdonald; </ParaText><ParaText id="3437488">Commemorating the centennial of the First World War and the 75th anniversary of the Second World War, and the enormous sacrifices made by Canadians and our Allies in both;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437489">Re-dedicating the National War Memorial to the memory of all men and women who fought for our country;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437490">Building a Memorial to the Victims of Communism, to remember the millions who suffered under tyranny; </ParaText><ParaText id="3437491">Marking the end of Canada’s mission in Afghanistan by honouring the service of our men and women in uniform, including those who made the ultimate sacrifice combating the spread of terrorism;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437492">Honouring the proud history of our Canadian Armed Forces by restoring military traditions;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437493">Strengthening the Cadet and Junior Ranger programs;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437494">Establishing the Canadian Museum of History to share the story of Canada with pride;</ParaText><ParaText id="3437495">Supporting the Pan and Parapan American Games and the FIFA Women’s World Cup in 2015, showcasing Canadians’ proud, competitive and united spirit under the maple leaf; and</ParaText><ParaText id="3437496">Working with Canadians to support community projects, local celebrations, and other initiatives to commemorate this historic occasion. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437497">The coming anniversary of Confederation is also a time to mark the contribution of Canada’s First Nations, Métis and Inuit communities, who have had a defining role in shaping our country. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437498">Our Government will continue our dialogue on the treaty relationship and comprehensive land claims.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437499">And our Government will continue to work in partnership with Aboriginal peoples to create healthy, prosperous, self-sufficient communities. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437500">The road to 2017 is a fitting time to strengthen our institutions and democratic processes.

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437501">The Government continues to believe the status quo in the Senate of Canada is unacceptable. The Senate must be reformed or, as with its provincial counterparts, vanish. The Government will proceed upon receiving the advice of the Supreme Court.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437502">And, the Government will propose changes to Canada’s elections laws to uphold the integrity of our voting system. Legislation will be introduced in time for implementation prior to the next federal election.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437503"><B>Conclusion</B></ParaText><ParaText id="3437504">Honourable Members of the Senate and Members of the Commons, as the dawn of our Confederation approached in the 1860s, our founding Prime Minister Sir John A. Macdonald said of Canada’s future that he saw “a great nation—great in thought, great in action, great in hope, and great in position.”</ParaText><ParaText id="3437505">His vision has come to pass. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437506">Today, Canada is a model for the world. Admired for our freedom. Respected for our principles. Envied for our openness, compassion and peaceful pluralism.

</ParaText><ParaText id="3437507">As we approach the 150th anniversary of our great land, we look to the future. A future we will face true to our character, the character of a determined and enterprising people: Canadians, whose shops and small businesses spur the growth of our towns and cities; who work factory shifts and drive taxicabs to help their families get ahead; who take the same pride in raising their children as they do in being citizens of the best country on earth. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437508">These are the quiet, unsung Canadians who are building our country. </ParaText><ParaText id="3437509">It is from them that we draw the inspiration to face an uncertain and unstable world.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437510">It is for them that we will seize the moment before us.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437511">Members of the House of Commons, you will be asked to appropriate the funds required to carry out the services and expenditures authorized by Parliament.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437512">Honourable Senators and Members of the House of Commons, you are the holders of a profound trust reposed in you by Canadians.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437513">May you be equal to that trust in all things and may Divine Providence guide you in your deliberations.</ParaText><Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="Mr. Harper" id="8096529"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="78738" Type="1">Right Hon. Stephen Harper (Prime Minister, CPC) </Affiliation></PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437515"> moved:</ParaText><ProceduralText TocType="TPC" id="3">Motion</ProceduralText><ParaText id="3437516"><Quote><QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">That the Speech of His Excellency the Governor General, delivered this day from the Throne to the two Houses of Parliament, be taken into consideration later this day. </QuotePara></Quote></ParaText><ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="4">(Motion agreed to)</ProceduralText></Content></Intervention></SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness>
			<SubjectOfBusiness id="8096489"><SubjectOfBusinessTitle>House of Commons Calendar</SubjectOfBusinessTitle><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096487"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437517">Pursuant to Standing Order 28(2)(b), I have the honour to lay upon the table the House of Commons calendar for the year 2014.</ParaText></Content></Intervention></SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness><SubjectOfBusiness id="8096533"><SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Federal Electoral Boundaries Commission</SubjectOfBusinessTitle><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096532"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437518">I have the honour to lay upon the table a certified copy of the report of the Federal Electoral Boundaries Commission for the province of Ontario.</ParaText><FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3437519">Pursuant to section 22 of the Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act, the report was published and made public on Monday, September 30, 2013 in an extra edition of the <I>Canada Gazette</I>. </ParaText><FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3437520">This report is deemed referred to the Standing Committee on Procedure and House Affairs.</ParaText></Content></Intervention></SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness><SubjectOfBusiness id="8096536"><SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Board of Internal Economy</SubjectOfBusinessTitle><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096535"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437521">I have the honour to inform the House that Mr. Duncan, member for the electoral district of <Affiliation DbId="170742" Type="2">Vancouver Island North</Affiliation>, has been appointed member of the Board of Internal Economy in place of Mr. O'Connor, member for the electoral district of <Affiliation DbId="170107" Type="2">Carleton—Mississippi Mills</Affiliation>, for the purposes and under the provisions of section 50 of the Parliament of Canada Act.</ParaText></Content></Intervention></SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness><SubjectOfBusiness id="8096555"><SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Business of Supply</SubjectOfBusinessTitle><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Clement" id="8096537"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170841" Type="4">Hon. Tony Clement (President of the Treasury Board, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ProceduralText TocType="TPC" id="5">Motion</ProceduralText><ParaText id="3437522"> Mr. Speaker, I move:</ParaText><ParaText id="3437523"><Quote><QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">That the business of supply be considered at the next sitting of the House. </QuotePara></Quote></ParaText></Content></Intervention><Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096538"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437524">Is it the pleasure of the House to adopt the motion?</ParaText><ParaText id="3437525"><B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText><ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="6">(Motion agreed to)</ProceduralText></Content></Intervention><FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="Mr. Van Loan" id="8096490"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170693" Type="4">Hon. Peter Van Loan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437526">Mr. Speaker, I move, seconded by the chief government whip, that, notwithstanding any Standing Order or usual practice of the House, the ordinary hour of daily adjournment of today's sitting be 8 p.m.</ParaText></Content></Intervention><FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096491"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437527">Does the hon. government House leader have the unanimous consent of the House to propose this motion?</ParaText><ParaText id="3437528"><B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437529"><B>Some hon. members:</B> No.</ParaText></Content></Intervention><Timestamp Hr="18" Mn="30">(1830)</Timestamp><Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096541"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437530">It is my duty to inform the House that a total of five days will be allotted for the supply period ending December 10, 2013.</ParaText></Content></Intervention></SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness><SubjectOfBusiness id="8096544"><SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Committee of the Whole</SubjectOfBusinessTitle><SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Appointment of Deputy Chair</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096543"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437531">I am now prepared to propose for the ratification of the House a candidate for the position of deputy chair of committee of the whole. </ParaText><FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><ProceduralText TocType="TPC" id="7">Motion</ProceduralText><ParaText id="3437532">Pursuant to Standing Order 8, I propose Mr. Barry Devolin for the position of deputy chair of committee of the whole. </ParaText><FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ParaText id="3437533">This motion is deemed moved and seconded. Is it the pleasure of the House to adopt the motion?</ParaText><ParaText id="3437534"><B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText><ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="8">(Motion agreed to)</ProceduralText></Content></Intervention>
				</SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness><SubjectOfBusiness id="8096546"><FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Appointment of Assistant Deputy Chair</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096545"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437535">I am now prepared to propose for the ratification of the House a candidate for the position of assistant deputy chair of committee of the whole. </ParaText><FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><ProceduralText TocType="TPC" id="9">Motion</ProceduralText><ParaText id="3437536">Pursuant to Standing Order 8, I propose Mr. Bruce Stanton for the position of assistant deputy chair of committee of the whole. This motion is deemed moved and seconded. Is it the pleasure of the House to adopt the motion?</ParaText><ParaText id="3437537"><B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText><ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="10">(Motion agreed to)</ProceduralText></Content></Intervention><Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="Mr. Van Loan" id="8096513"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170693" Type="4">Hon. Peter Van Loan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437538">Mr. Speaker, I propose that notwithstanding any Standing Order or usual practice of the House, when government Motion No. 1 is called, no member shall speak for more than 10 minutes, with no question and comment period, provided that members may divide their time with another member; the Speaker shall not receive any amendments; and when no member rises to speak or after 40 minutes of debate, whichever is earlier, the motion shall be deemed adopted on division.</ParaText></Content></Intervention><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096514"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437539">Does the hon. government House leader have the unanimous consent of the House to propose the motion?</ParaText><ParaText id="3437540"><B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText><ParaText id="3437541"><B>Some hon. members:</B> No.</ParaText></Content></Intervention></SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness><SubjectOfBusiness id="8096562"><FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage><SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Committees of the House</SubjectOfBusinessTitle><SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Procedure and House Affairs </SubjectOfBusinessQualifier><SubjectOfBusinessContent><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Duncan (Vancouver Island North)" id="8096515"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="194603" Type="96">Hon. John Duncan (Minister of State and Chief Government Whip, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ProceduralText TocType="TPC" id="11">Motion</ProceduralText><ParaText id="3437542">Mr. Speaker, I move:</ParaText><ParaText id="3437543"><Quote><QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">That the membership of the Standing Committee on Procedure and House Affairs be amended as follows:</QuotePara></Quote></ParaText><ParaText id="3437544"><Quote><QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">Brad Butt for Scott Armstrong;</QuotePara></Quote></ParaText><ParaText id="3437545"><Quote><QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">Ted Opitz for Parm Gill;</QuotePara></Quote></ParaText><ParaText id="3437546"><Quote><QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">Blake Richards for Costas Menegakis; and</QuotePara></Quote></ParaText><ParaText id="3437547"><Quote><QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">Kevin Lamoureux for Dominic LeBlanc</QuotePara></Quote></ParaText></Content></Intervention><FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096517"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437548">Is it the pleasure of the House to adopt the motion?</ParaText><ParaText id="3437549"><B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText><ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="12">(Motion agreed to)</ProceduralText></Content></Intervention><Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="8096519"><PersonSpeaking><Affiliation DbId="170958" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking><Content><ParaText id="3437550">It being 6:30 p.m., the House stands adjourned until tomorrow at 10 a.m., pursuant to Standing Order 24(1).</ParaText><ParaText id="3437551">(The House adjourned at 6:30 p.m.) </ParaText></Content></Intervention></SubjectOfBusinessContent></SubjectOfBusiness></OrderOfBusiness></HansardBody></Hansard>
